Mss.Ms.Coll.72
American Philosophical Society
- Series III. Rebecca Gratz, 1795-1867; Personal correspondence to Rebecca Gratz, seventh child of Michael and Miriam Gratz, from her sisters, in-laws, nieces, nephews, and friends from 1795-1867. Contains letters with descriptions of social activities of family members and their personal views on e
  - Papers, 1795-1867
    - Ewing, Margaret, 1803-1808, undated
    - Ewing, Margaret, 1803-1809, undated
    - Ewing, Samuel, 1803, undated
    - Fisher, Sarah W., 1864 October 5
    - Fenno, George, Undated
    - Fenno, Harriet, 1799-1800, undated
    - Fenno, Maria, 1795-1799
      Friend.
    - Fenno, Maria, 1800 January-August
    - Fenno, Maria, 1800 September-December
    - Fenno, Maria, 1801 January-June
    - Fenno, Maria, 1801 July-December
    - Fenno, Maria, 1802
    - Fenno, Mary Elizabeth, 1802-1809
    - Fox, Marian, 1862 October 11
    - Fox, Mary D., 1856, undated
    - Gilpin, Eliza, Undated
    - Gratz, Anna, 1862-1863
    - Gratz, Anna Maria, 1844-1847
      Mrs. Benjamin Gratz.
    - Gratz, Anna Maria, 1862-1866
    - Gratz, Barnard, 1797 November 5
    - Gratz, Benjamin, 1817-1830
      Brother.
    - Gratz, Benjamin, 1844-1860, undated
    - Gratz, H.H., 1845-1846
    - Gratz, Hyman, 1804-1856
    - Gratz, Hyman, 1835 September 15
      To Rebecca and Benjamin
    - Gratz, Hyman, 1812
      To the Misses Gratz.
    - Gratz, Jacob, 1815-1856, undated
    - Gratz, Joseph, 1810-1855, undated
    - Gratz, Joseph, 1810-1820, undated
    - Gratz, M.C., 1857-1858
      Mrs. H.H. Gratz
    - Gratz, Miriam, 1862
    - Gratz, Miriam Simon, 1797 June 8
      Mother.
    - Gratz, Miriam Simon and Richea Gratz Hays, 1797 June 18
      Mother and Sister.
    - Gratz, Miriam Simon and Sarah Gratz, 1798, 1808
    - Gratz, Rachel, 1798-1799
    - Gratz, Rachel, 1800
    - Gratz, Rachel, 1802-1805
    - Gratz, Rachel, 1806-1808, undated
    - Gratz, Rachel and Maria Fenno, 1806 December 7
      Sister and Friend.
    - Gratz, Rachel and Miriam Simon Gratz, 1799 February 24
      Sister and Mother.
    - Gratz, Rachel and M.F. Hoffman, Undated
    - Gratz, Rachel and Solomon Moses, 1809 September 8
      Sister and Brother-in-law.
    - Gratz, Sarah, 1797-1799
    - Gratz, Sarah, 1800-1806
    - Gratz, Sarah, 1807
    - Gratz, Sarah, 1808
    - Gratz, Sarah, 1810, undated
    - Gratz, Sarah, 1807 July 1
      To Rebecca; Rachel Gratz Moses to Miriam Simon Gratz.
    - Hall, John E., 1806-1808
    - Hall, S., 1819
    - Hart, L.B., 1864, undated
    - Hart, Louisa B., 1864 March 4
    - Hays, Catherine and Slowey, 1812-1822, undated
    - Hays, Ellen, 1818-1821
    - Hays, I.M., 1835 June 29
    - Hays, Richea Gratz, 1797-1847
    - Hays, Richea Gratz and Ellen Hays Etting, 1844 June 17
    - Hays, Richea Gratz and Sarah Gratz, 1798 September 5
      Sisters.
    - Hays, Richea Gratz and Rosa Marx, 1844-1847
    - Hays, Richea Gratz and Sara G. Mordecai, 1847 August 5
    - Hays, Rosa, 1835 August 2
    - Hays, Slowey, 1812-1832
    - Hays, Slowey and Catherine, 1828 October 20
    - Hays, Slowey and Helen, 1812 October 6
    - Hodge, P.G.A., Undated
    - Hoffman, Ann, 1804-1809
    - Hoffman, Joseph Ogden, 1804-1806
    - Hoffman, Julia, 1837-1856
    - Hoffman, Maria, 1803-1809
    - Hoffman, P.N., Undated
    - Hopkinson, E., Undated
    - Hopkinson, Joseph, 1808 February 6
    - Irving, Washington, 1807 November 4
      Newspaper clipping, regarding Thomas Sully.
    - Jewish Foster Home, 1866
      Evelyn Bomeister.
    - Jewish Sunday School, 1862 March 4
    - Joseph, Lizzie Lee, Undated
    - Joseph, Sara G., 1850-1857
    - Joseph, Sara G., 1858-1862
    - Joseph, Sara G., 1867-1868
      To Rebecca Gratz and Horace Moses.
    - Joseph, Sara G., 1863-1867, undated
    - Kemble, Fanny, 1846-1858, undated
      Actress.
    - Lee, Elizabeth B., 1849-1864, undated
    - Lesser, Isaac, 1822, 1856
    - Levy, M.E., 1852 May 5
    - Levy, Richea, 1810-1820
    - Marx, Rosa, 1836 June 24
    - Meredith, Gertrude G., 1805, undated
    - Meredith, Miriam G., 1841, 1864
    - Meredith, Mrs., 1806-1813, undated
    - Mordecai, Laura, 1860 September 23
    - Mordecai, Miriam, Undated
    - Moses, Gratzio A., 1856, 1865
    - Moses, Horace, 1846
    - Moses, Mary, 1856
    - Moses, Mary Ashe, Undated
    - Moses, Miriam G., 1829, 1835, 1859
    - Moses, Miriam and Rebecca, Undated
      Nieces.
    - Moses, Rachel Gratz, 1807-1808
    - Moses, Rachel Gratz, 1809
    - Moses, Rachel Gratz, 1810-1817
    - Moses, Rachel Gratz, 1818-1819, undated
    - Moses, Rachel Gratz and Sally M. Cohen, 1808, undated
    - Moses, Rachel Gratz and Solomon Moses, 1807 July 12
    - Moses, Sara Gratz, 1836-1846
    - Moses, Sara Gratz, 1847, 1855
    - Moses, Solomon, 1809-1810; 1855-1857
    - Moses, Solomon and Sarah Gratz, 1807 June 30
    - My dear aunt, Undated
      ______ to ...
    - Myers, Adeline, 1819-1826, undated
    - Myers, J., 1835 March 22
    - Myers, L., 1810 September 17
    - Nathan, Gratz, 1863
    - Nathan, Jonathan, 1862 February 26
    - Nathan, Rachel G. and Rebecca G.`, 1861
    - Nathan, Rebecca G., 1841-1857
    - Nathan, Rebecca G., 1860-1861
    - Nathan, Rebecca G., 1862-1863
    - Nathan, Rebecca G., 1864, undated
    - Newlin, Anna P., 1861 May 1
    - Nicholas, Charles J., 1806
    - Ogden, Isabella W., 1808
    - Ogden, L.M., 1806 March 22-24
    - Paulding, J.K., 1845 October 7
    - Receipts, 1812, 1814
    - Riggs, E., 1856 June 27
    - Riggs, Mary, 1857-1864
    - Rodman, Harriet, 1804 June 18
    - Rutledge, Edward, 1830 January 9
    - Samson, Sarah, 1861 April 5
    - Schroeder, Henrietta, 1847-1862
    - Schuyler, Shinah, 1797, undated
      Aunt.
    - Schuyler, V.?, 1813-1814
    - Sedgwick, Catherine, 1830-1854, undated
    - Unidentified, 1852, undated
    - VanRensalaer, Henrietta, 1861 May 21
    - Vansallear?, 1847 June 8
    - Williams, Julia, 1842 July 18
    - Wise, J.M., Undated
- Series IV. Rachel Gratz Moses, 1797-1823; Personal correspondence to Rachel Gratz Moses, eighth child of Michael and Miriam Gratz, primarily from her sisters Rebecca, Sarah and Frances, with some notes from her husband Solomon and friend Mary Fenno, 1797-1823. Contains two subseries of letters, 1832-1879, to her children Horace Moses and Sara Gratz Moses Joseph, regarding family and some legal matters.
  Rachel Gratz (1783-1823) was married to Solomon Moses on June 24, 1806. They had nine children of whom six lived to adulthood. They include: Isaac (1807-1847), Miriam Gratz (b.1808) married Solomon Cohen (1802-1875), Rebecca Gratz (1810-1891) married Jonathan Nathan, Harriet (1812), Simon Gratz (1815-1897) married Mary Ashe in 1838, and Mary Acheson in 1855, Edmund (1815), Sara Gratz (b.1817) married Jacob Henry Joseph (1814-1907), Horace (1820-1893) married Mary Hallahan Fox, and Gertrude (1822-1823). Upon her death in 1823, her children were cared for by the Gratz family.
  - Papers, 1797-1823
    - Etting, Frances Gratz, 1799-1802
    - Etting, Frances Gratz, 1803-1804
    - Etting, Frances Gratz, 1806, undated
    - Fenno, Harriet, 1800
    - Fenno, Mary Elizabeth, 1802-1803
    - Fenno, Mary Elizabeth, 1804-1806
    - Gratz, Barnard, 1799 February 5
    - Gratz, Rebecca, 1798
    - Gratz, Rebecca, 1799-1800
    - Gratz, Rebecca, 1801-1802
    - Gratz, Rebecca, 1803
    - Gratz, Rebecca, 1804 April-July
    - Gratz, Rebecca, 1804 August-September
    - Gratz, Rebecca, 1805-1807
    - Gratz, Rebecca and Miriam, 1800 December 26
    - Gratz, Rebecca and Richea Gratz Hays, 1802, 1804
    - Gratz, Rebecca and Sarah, 1804-1805
    - Gratz, Sarah, 1797-1799
    - Gratz, Sarah, 1800
    - Gratz, Sarah, 1802-1804
    - Gratz, Sarah, 1805-1814, undated
    - Gratz, Sarah and Harriet Fenno, 1804 August 24
    - Gratz, Simon, 1806
    - Hamilton, Rebecca, Undated
    - Hoffman, Ann, 1804-1806
    - Inscription, 1823
      Epitaph for Rachel Gratz Moses and her daughter, Gertrude.
    - Levy, Richea, Undated
    - Meredith, Gertrude, 1810, 1823
    - Meredith, Mrs., 1810 October 14
    - Moses, Solomon, 1806-1824, undated
    - Moses, Solomon, 1801-1851, undated
      Rachel Gratz and others, including Stephen Girard to...
    - Rodman, Harriet, 1803-1805, undated
    - Rodman, John, 1804 August 6
    - Schuyler, Shinah, 1798-1805
    - Unidentified, Undated
      Rachel Gratz to...
  - Horace Moses, 1844-1879
    - Achburn, Richard, 1855 December 1
      Horace Moses to...
    - Bolling, S.J., 1879 February 5
    - Centennial, 1876
      Label from wine bottle in Joseph Gratz hand. Contents of bottle consumed during the Centennial year, 1876
    - Cramond, H., 1859 October 31
    - Cullen, R.D., 1856 January 11
    - Gratz, Hyman, 1844
    - Gratz, Rebecca, 1856-1857, undated
    - Gratz, Rebecca -- Will, 1869 September 7
    - Hart, Louise B., 1865, undated
    - Hart, Louise B., 1865
    - Hays, Isaac, 1859 May
    - Homan, John Henry, 1863 August 29
      Substitute, volunteer enlistment, United States military service.
    - Inventory and appraisement, Undated
    - Jewish Hospital, 1878 October 1
    - Joseph, Sara G. Moses, 1867-1868, undated
    - Joseph, Sara G. Moses, 1865-1869
    - Lee, S.P., 1867-1869
    - Locust Street House, 1859 April 14
    - Moses, Mary Hallahan Fox, Undated
      Wife.
    - Moses, Solomon, 1843-1853
      Father.
    - Mordecai, Sara, 1859, undated
    - Receipts, 1847-1879, undated
  - Sara Gratz Moses Joseph, 1832-1879
    - Ada, Undated
    - Cohen, Miriam G., 1866 July 25
    - David, M.E., 1848, 1867, undated
    - Diary, Journal, 1832-1846, undated
    - Envelopes, Undated
    - Essays, 1832, undated
    - Gratz, Rebecca, Undated
    - Hart, L., Undated
    - Hart, Mary, Undated
    - Kemble, Fanny, 1848
    - Marriage contract, 1848 May 3
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
      Parchment.
    - Moses, Lavinia, 1849 February 11
    - Moses, Marian, 1879 May 27
    - Myers, Adeline, Undated
    - Postcard, Undated
    - Robinson, R.E., Undated
    - Unidentified, Undated
- Series V. Sarah Gratz, 1800-1808; Personal correspondence to Sarah Gratz, sixth child of Michael and Miriam Gratz, from her sisters Frances, Rebecca and Rachel with notes from her friend Harriet Rodman. The bulk of the letters are from Rebecca, from 1800-1807, concerning family matters.
  Sarah (Sally) Gratz (1779-1817) shared the same literary and social interests as her younger sister Rebecca. Close in age, they were companions as well as siblings, socializing with many of the same friends.
  - Etting, Frances Gratz, 1803 November 24
  - Gratz, Rachel, Undated
  - Gratz, Rebecca, 1800-1807, undated
  - Moses, Rachel Gratz and Rebecca, 1806 September 7
  - Rodman, Harriet, 1808 May 18
- Series VI. Miscellaneous, 1786-1974; A collection of author's notes, bound volumes, maps, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, correspondence, and poems all related to the Gratz family. Includes John F. Marion's research notes for an intended biography of Rebecca Gratz, a travel journal of an 1807 trip to Kentucky, a 1842 letter from Andrew Jackson discussing individuals and courtship, a calling card from the Prince of Wales, silhouettes, sketches and invitations. A third of the correspondence pertains to Joseph Boneparte, Napoleon III, Prince and Princess Murat. These letters, all in French, were collected by family member Miriam Fox. Of note, pamphlets and notes on the three organizations founded by Rebecca: The Philadelphia Orphan Society, the Hebrew Sunday School, and the Female Hebrew Benevolent Society. Also of note, poems dedicated to family members, some on birch bark.
  - Author Notes, various dates
    - Biography of Rebecca Gratz and Family, Box #1
      Author John F. Marion's research notes. Contains genealogical information and copies of family letters from other archives.
    - Biography of Rebecca Gratz and Family, Box #2
  - Bound Volumes, 1807-1892
    - Index to Portfolio, Undated
    - Receipts, 1813-1820
    - Receipts, 1858-1867, 1876, 1892
      Estate of J. Gratz.
    - Travel Diary, 1807
      From Louisville to Nashville.
  - Maps, Undated
    - Harrisburg to Pittsburg, Undated
      Projected Railway... with proposed extensions to Cleveland, Cincinnati, and St. Louis, in connexion (sic) with the Public Works of Pennsylvania, Ohio, Indiana, and Illinois.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1773-1939, undated
    - Bonaparte, Joseph--Residence, Undated
      Bordentown, New Jersey.
    - Empress Eugenie, Undated
    - Gratz, Michael--Estate, Undated
      Obituary of Miriam Cohen, poem "Contentment," Philadelphia Merchants.
    - Gratz, Rebecca, Undated
      Regarding Rebecca as a prototype of a character in Walter Scott's Ivanhoe.
    - Indian Appropriation Bill, Undated
    - Kemble, Fanny, 1872, undated
      Actress and author. Contains photographs.
    - Liberty, 1939 January 28
      Color magazine cover.
    - O'Neill, Miss, Undated
    - Pennsylvania legislature, Undated
      Regarding secession.
    - The Philadelphia Pulpit, Undated
      Article by Isaac Lesser. With 3 other clippings: Jewish Cemetery at Newport, Song of the shirt, poem by Thomas Hood, and Light of the Lighthouse poem by Epes Sargent.
    - Postscript to the Pennsylvania Gazette, 1773 December 24
      A facsimile. With 10 other clippings, primarily poems.
    - The Sanitary Reporter, 1863 September 15
  - Pamphlets, 1849-1869
    - Christy's Minstrels, Bouffes Americains, 1859
      ...Repertoire. With insert noting a program of works performed on February 24 for the Hutchinson Family.
    - Female Hebrew Benevolent Society, 1858
      The constitution of...
    - Philadelphia Orphan Society, 1857
      Forty-second annual report...read at the anniversary meeting, May 12, 1857.
    - Reverend S. Morais--Address, 1869
      ...delivered before the managers and pupils of the Hebrew Sunday School, on the life and character of Miss Rebecca Gratz, its founder and first directress.
    - Schiller's Song of the Bell, 1849
      A new translation by W.H. Furness.
  - Papers, 1786-1974
    - Arthur to H. Joseph, 1810, 1817
    - Astor, John Jacob to Messrs. Montmollin and Moses, 1813 October 14
    - Birth Announcements, 1866
      Duke and Duchess De Mouchy, Mr. Vandal.
    - Bonaparte, Jerome N. to My dear cousin, 1861 July 27
    - Bonaparte, Joseph to ______, 1839 September 25
    - Bonaparte, Julie to ______, 1820 January 1
    - Burr, Aaron to Isaac Moses, 1786 December 22
    - Calling cards, 1881, undated
      Duke of Edinburgh, Manuel Grosso, Lady Cowley, Prince of Wales and others.
    - Cards, 1867, 1872, undated
      Holiday and dance programmes.
    - Certificates, 1887
      Verifying signatures of Edwin H. Fitler and G.B. Benner.
    - Cowley, Olivia Cecelia to Princess Murat, Undated
    - Currency, 1790, 1864
      Two pence given to Elkalah M. Cohen by her father Solomon Myers Cohen. Confederate bond to Octavus Cohen for $10,000.
    - Davies, Samuel and Matilda A. Joseph, 1818 December 8
      Marriage certificate.
    - Envelopes, 1794-1882, undated
    - Essays
      Minstrelsy, Rollin's Ancient history.
    - Etting, Josephine to Augusta L. Ragois, Undated
    - Eugenie to Napoleon III, 1863 September 1
      Empress Consort to Emperor of France
    - Eugenie to Princess Murat, 1855-1864, undated
      Empress Consort to Napoleon III
    - Female Hebrew Benevolent Society, 1835-1870, undated
    - Fox, J.H. to ______, Undated
    - Fox, Marian to ______, 1863 February 16
      Regarding a visit from the Emperor and Empress of France.
    - Fragments, Undated
    - Garde Nationale de la Seine, 1849 April 13
    - Gratz family, Undated
      Genealogy.
    - Hamilton, R. to Sally, Undated
    - Hart, Joel, MD, 1816 July 8
      Bris for Jacob Joseph.
    - Hays, I. Minis to Henry [Clay?], 1893 March 24
    - Hebrew Sunday School, 1841, 1865, undated
    - Invitations, 1856, 1865, 1915, undated
      Lady Cowley; Wedding--Princess Anna Murat to Duke De Mouchy; Historical Society of Pennsylvania; Duke and Duchess of Connaught.
    - Jackson, Andrew to F.P. Blair, 1842 September 26
    - Joseph, Ethel, 1934
    - Joseph, Gratz to John F. Marion, 1974 October 21
    - Joseph, Henry, 1930
    - Komar, Count to Princess Murat, Undated
    - Levy, M.E. to Elias Yulee, 1851 March 28
    - List of books, 1848-1858, 1969
      Read by H.M. [Horace Moses?]; Dorchester House Library.
    - Margaret, Louise to Mrs. Henry Joseph, Undated
    - Matilda to Grandma, 1864 June 24
    - Mordecai, Misses, Undated
      Day School for Children
    - Morris, Robert to Isaac Moses, 1786 July 25
    - Moses, Isaac, Undated
      Biographical information.
    - Moses, Lionel to Henry Joseph, 1928 June 22
    - Murat, Caroline L.A. to Mrs. Fox, 1844 November 21
      Watercolor sketch.
    - Murat, Louis to Marian Fox, 1863 August 18
      Poem on the anniversary of his Mother's marriage to Prince Murat.
    - Murat, Louise to Lucien Murat, 1825 July 22
      A daughter of Caroline and the King, Joachim Murat.
    - Napoleon, Letizia to My dear cousin, 1816 May 16
      Princess De Camarata?
    - Napoleon, Marie Clotilde to Princess Caroline Murat, 1859 May 26
      French.
    - Napoleon III to Prince Murat, 1853, 1863
    - Notes, 1807-1883, undated
    - Obituaries, Undated
      Elizabeth Hall; David Moses; Harriet Fenno Rodman.
    - Orphan Society, 1862, undated
    - Port of Philadelphia, Undated
    - Powers of attorney, 1851, 1887
      Rebecca G. Moses Nathan to Solomon Moses; Louisa Hart Pitcairn to Gershon Joseph.
    - ______ to Prince Lucien Murat, 1861-1863, undated
      Mr. and Mrs. Haussman; Mr. and Mrs. Amedee Dailly; Louis Napoleon?
    - ______ to Princess Anna Murat, 1859-1863, undated
      Prince Napoleon and Princess Clotilde; Princess de Metternich; Count de Morny.
    - Princess Mathilde to Dear cousin, Undated
      Daughter of Jerome Bonaparte
    - ______ to Princess Murat, 1849-1863, undated
      Napoleon III; President of Republic of France; Countess Waleurska?; Alvarez De Tolede.
    - Receipts, 1866, 1894
    - ______ to Robert Walsh, Undated
    - Saint James Club, Montreal to J.H. Joseph, 1904 April 22
    - Schuyler, Shinah to Joseph Simon, 1797 October
      Daughter to Father.
    - Silhouettes, 1803-1843, undated
    - Sketches, 1855, undated
      One of Napoleon; contains black and white negative.
    - Theatre programs, 1867 January-February
      With dance cards.
    - Tyndall, John to Charles Walkem, Undated
    - Unidentified, 1862-1865, undated
    - Walkem, Charles to Charlotte Boomer, 1844 September 1
  - Poetry, Prayers, Music, 1798-1873
    - All the World's a Stage, Undated
      By Rebecca Gratz.
    - Birch Bark, 1806-1807, undated
      Written on bark by Rebecca Gratz and Violetta.
    - Caldwell, James, Undated
      In memory.
    - DeVandreuil, Jeanne, by, Undated
    - Fenno, Caroline, to, Undated
      Fragment.
    - Gratz, Miriam Simon, 1808 November 1
      To honor her death.
    - Gratz, R. to Miriam Simon Gratz, Undated
      Written by Rebecca Gratz for her Mother's birthday.
    - Hymn, 1840 February 27
      Dedicated to Miss Gratz by H.A. Hadry.
    - Hymn--Meditation at Twilight, Undated
      Musical score.
    - Malbone, Mr., to, Undated
      Unique stationery.
    - Moses, Horace to Sara G. Moses, Undated
      On her 17th birthday. (brother to sister)
    - Ode to Napoleon Bonaparte, Undated
      By Sara G. Joseph?
    - Poems, 1798-1873
    - Poems, Undated
    - Prayers, Undated
    - Ware, Ellen, Undated
- Series VII. Artifacts, 1805-1900, undated; Objects of family clothing, wallets, hair and pressed flowers. Of note, a daguerrotype (subject unknown), a beaded bag, a cotton bonnet, and several locks of hair. Also, a marriage contract in Hebrew.
  - Marriage contract, 1835; #1
    Charles Marx to Elizabeth R. Etting.
  - Beaded bag, cotton bonnet, Undated; #2
    Bag belonged to Rebecca Gratz.
  - Contents of green and black wallet, Undated; #3
    Contents of a wallet owned by Solomon Moses: a lock of blond hair and two newspaper clippings, one related to yellow fever and the other a sonnet by Daniel Webster. Contents of wallet owned by Jacob Gratz: survey of lots along Barr's Avenue.
  - Wallet, booklet and daguerreotype, Undated; #4
    Brown wallet belonged to Jacob Gratz, green and black wallet belonged to Solomon Moses, small satin booklet, and daguerreotype portrait of unknown subject.
  - Foliage, Undated
  - Hair, Undated
    Unidentified.
  - Hair--Ada and Emmet, Undated
  - Hair--Gratz, 1900 December 9
  - Hair--Gratz, Joseph to Rebecca Gratz, 1835 August 10
  - Hair--Harriet's for R.G. Moses, Undated
  - Hair--Meredith, Gertrude to Rebecca Gratz, 1805 June 4
  - Hair--Moses, Marian, 1884 November 10
  - Ribbon--Rodman, Harriet to Rachel Gratz, Undated
  - Small straw broom--impression, Undated